Guide to the Montana Department of Transportation, Great Falls District Office records 1935-1991
Montana Historical Society
Montana Department of Transportation, Great Falls District Office records
1935-1991
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 406
Montana. Department of Transportation.
13.2 linear feet
Records of the Department of Transportation, Great Falls District Office are correspondence, subject files, and meeting minutes related to project planning, design, general maintenance, personnel, and public relations issues at the Great Falls District Office and district’s area office in Havre. Correspondence, files and minutes were primarily kept by the District Engineer.
The Montana State Highway Commission was created in 1913 by the state Legislative Assembly. The original Commission was composed of three members. In 1917 new legislation altered the organization of the Commission by authorizing the appointment of twelve members according to geographic highway districts. Membership was changed again in 1921 to three members appointed by the Governor and in 1941 to five members, also appointed by the Governor. In 1971 the Commission was renamed the Montana Department of Highways, created by Chapter 7 of the Executive Reorganization Act of 1971 and implemented by executive order of the Governor on December 16, 1971. The Department of Highways took over all but the advisory functions of the State Highway Commission.
By 1972, the Department consisted of seven divisions: the Legal Division, Personnel Division, Centralized Services Division, Engineering Division, Motor Pool Division, Gross Vehicle Weight Division, and the Maintenance Division. Each division is headed by an administrator. The Centralized Services Division, Engineering Division, Motor Pool Division, Gross Vehicle Weight Division, and the Maintenance Division are furthered sub-divided into bureaus, headed by Chiefs. In 1991, the Department of Highways became the Department of Transportation. This was primarily a name change. However, there were some structural and administrative changes.
The Highway Department, the Department of Highways, and Department of Transportation maintained regional offices in the five commissioner districts: Billings, Butte, Glendive, Great Falls, and Missoula. The District Engineer (later called the District Administrator) was the chief administrative officer in each district office. District office files document the activities of the district administrators, engineers, maintenance crew, and other district office employees. The district offices addressed administrative, functional, and project related issues of their particular area, including: highway needs, current construction projects, HR/training for employees, road design, federal and state aid and grants, reports to the Department of Highways/ Department of Transportation in Helena regarding general maintenance, construction, and area concerns, etc. District administrators held meetings every 6 weeks. Other employees in the district and area offices also attended duty-specific meetings with outside district staff members; including maintenance crew meetings, engineer meetings etc., in order to maintain consistent communication among the districts and with other state agencies regarding programs, projects, and district goals. The files in the district office were kept by the District Engineer/Administrator.
Records (1935-1991) of the Montana Department of Highways, Great Falls District Office, consist of the correspondence, meeting minutes and subject files of the Great Falls District and area offices, including the Havre Area Office. The records include correspondence files (1935-1993), subject files (1941-1997) and meeting minutes (1997-1998). Subject files are primarily correspondence which relate to specific subjects. The records document the function, operation, and communication of the offices that fell within the Great Falls District. Both correspondence and subject files document: general and special maintenance projects of highways, bridges, and signs; public concerns; municipal concerns and projects; Federal and State grants and funding, including Works Project Administration era projects; civil defense and transportation concerns; accident and safety monitoring; as well as district budget and project planning. A large portion of the files document flood damage, flood control, and repair projects.
The Great Falls District Files are arranged into 2 subgroups: The Great Falls District Office records, which are arranged into Correspondence and Subject files; and the Havre Area Office records, which are arranged into Correspondence and Meeting Minutes.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Roads--Design and construction--Administration--Montana.; Transportation. --Montana.
Helena (Mont.)--Politics and government; Great Falls (Mont.); Havre (Mont.)
Montana; Transportation
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Great Falls District Office, 1935-1989
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence (accidents, encroachments), 1935-1965 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Correspondence (equipment, guardrails, Maintenance Engineer), 1935-1965 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Correspondence (historic markers, road condition reports, Maintenance Engineer), 1935-1965 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Correspondence (Preconstruction), 1944-1961 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Correspondence (Personnel and Payroll), 1945-1962 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Correspondence (sectionmen, weed control, Maintenance Engineer), 1935-1964 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Correspondence (Havre), 1964-1969 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Correspondence (construction Memos Re: Right of Way), 1947-1960 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Correspondence (pre-construction), 1953 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Correspondence (Bureau of Public Roads, Public Roads Administration Procedures), 1942-1959 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Correspondence (Construction Practices and Reports), 1948-1968 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Correspondence (general memos), 1936-1940 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Correspondence (general memos), 1949-1955 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - Correspondence (general memos), 1958-1965 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - Correspondence (general), 1964-1982 (Box-folder 2)
    - Correspondence (general), 1983-1985 (Box-folder 3)
    - Correspondence (general), 1985-1987 (Box-folder 4)
    - Correspondence (general), 1987-1989 (Box-folder 5)
    - Correspondence (general), 1989-1991 (Box-folder 6)
    - Correspondence (general), 1991 (Box-folder 7)
  - Subject Files
    - Bureau of Public Roads, Inspections, 1964 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Construction Reports, Monthly, 1964 (Box-folder 8/2)
    - Construction Funds, Status of Interstate, 1964 (Box-folder 8/3)
    - County Planning Surveys, Cascade County, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 8/4)
    - County Planning Surveys, Choteau County, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 8/5)
    - County Planning Surveys, Lewis and Clark County, 1950 (Box-folder 8/6)
    - County Planning Surveys, Pondera County, 1949 (Box-folder 8/7)
    - County Planning Surveys, Teton County, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 8/8)
    - Flood Damage Costs and Accounting, 1964 (Box-folder 8/9)
    - Flood Damage Repair, 1964 (Box-folder 8/10)
    - Flood Damage and Secondary Roads, 1964 (Box-folder 8/11)
    - Flood Damage, Federal Aid / Emergency Relief, 1964 (Box-folder 8/12)
    - Flood Damage, Construction and Emergency Relief, 1964 (Box-folder 8/13)
    - Forest Highway Projects, 1941-1962 (Box-folder 8/14)
    - General Maintenance / Snow Removal, 1964 (Box-folder 8/15)
    - Laboratory Testing, Forms and Instructions, 1959 (Box-folder 8/16)
    - Planning Surveys, Federal Aid and Research Studies, 1964 (Box-folder 8/17)
    - Secondary Roads, 1964 (Box-folder 8/18)
    - Signs and Signage, 1964 (Box-folder 8/19)
    - Wage Scale and Public Employees Craft Council, 1965 (Box-folder 8/20)
    - Budget, 1966 (Box-folder 8/21)
    - Construction Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 8/22)
    - Final Inspection Reports, Federal, 1966 (Box-folder 8/23)
    - Funds: Status of State / Interstate Construction Funding, 1966 (Box-folder 8/24)
    - General Maintenance, 1966 (Box-folder 8/25)
    - Glacier National Park Guide Signs, 1966 (Box-folder 8/26)
    - Proposal,separation of 2nd and 10th Ave, Great Falls, 1966 (Box-folder 9/1)
    - Radiological Monitoring Program / Manual, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 9/2)
    - Secondary Roads, 1966 (Box-folder 9/3)
    - Blue Star Marker Garden Club, 1967 (Box-folder 9/4)
    - Budget, 1967 (Box-folder 9/5)
    - Bureau of Public Roads inspection Report, 1967 (Box-folder 9/6)
    - Civil Defense, 1967 (Box-folder 9/7)
    - Clippings, “New Roundup”, 1967 (Box-folder 9/8)
    - Construction Reports, 1967 (Box-folder 9/9)
    - Construction Engineering Costs, 1967 (Box-folder 9/10)
    - Funding: State of Construction Funds, 1967 (Box-folder 9/11)
    - General Maintenance, 1967 (Box-folder 9/12)
    - Planning Surveys Fatal Accidents, 1967 (Box-folder 9/13)
    - Secondary Roads, 1967 (Box-folder 9/14)
    - Signs and Signage, 1967 (Box-folder 9/15)
    - Budget, 1968 (Box-folder 9/16)
    - Bureau of Public Roads Inspection Report, 1968 (Box-folder 9/17)
    - Clippings, “New Roundup”, 1968 (Box-folder 9/18)
    - Construction Reports, 1968 (Box-folder 9/19)
    - Construction Funds, 1968 (Box-folder 9/20)
    - Dike System – Great Falls, 1968 (Box-folder 9/21)
    - Dupuyer Transfer Section, 1968 (Box-folder 9/22)
    - Flood Damage and Repair, 1968 (Box-folder 9/23)
    - General Maintenance, 1968 (Box-folder 9/24)
    - Right of Way General, 1963-1968 (Box-folder 9/25)
    - Special Maintenance and Betterment, 1968 (Box-folder 9/26)
    - Secondary Roads, 1968 (Box-folder 9/27)
    - Statewide Telephone and Telegraph Permit, 1968 (Box-folder 9/28)
    - Specifications for Fire Protection Project: Stage 1, 1968 (Box-folder 9/29)
    - Specifications for Fire Protection Project: Stage 1 – Maps, 1968 (Box-folder 9/30)
    - Flood Damage and Repair, 1968 (Box-folder 9/31)
    - Signs and Signage, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 9/32)
    - Special Maintenance and Betterment, 1969 (Box-folder 9/33)
    - Utility Agreements, 1969 (Box-folder 9/34)
    - Wage Scale and Public Employees Craft Council, 1969 (Box-folder 9/35)
    - Planning Surveys, 1969 (Box-folder 9/36)
    - Pre-Construction – General, 1969 (Box-folder 9/37)
    - Right of Way – General, 1969 (Box-folder 9/38)
    - Road Oil, 1965-1969 (Box-folder 9/39)
    - Budget, 1969 (Box-folder 10/1)
    - Bureau of Public Land Reports, 1969 (Box-folder 10/2)
    - Clippings, “News Roundup”, 1969 (Box-folder 10/3)
    - Construction Reports General, 1969 (Box-folder 10/4)
    - Construction Engineering Costs, 1969 (Box-folder 10/5)
    - Flood Damage, 1969 (Box-folder 10/6)
    - Funds: Status of Funds – Construction, 1969 (Box-folder 10/7)
    - General Maintenance, 1969 (Box-folder 10/8)
    - Signs and Signage, 1969 (Box-folder 10/9)
    - Bridges, 1953-1970 (Box-folder 10/10)
    - Budget, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 10/11)
    - Bureau of Public Roads Inspection Reports, 1970 (Box-folder 10/12)
    - Clippings, “News Roundup”, 1970 (Box-folder 10/13)
    - Commission, State Highway Policies and Organization, 1970 (Box-folder 10/14)
    - Construction General, 1970 (Box-folder 10/15)
    - Construction Engineering Costs, 1970 (Box-folder 10/16)
    - Funds: Status of Construction Funds, 1970 (Box-folder 10/17)
    - Forest Highways, Kings Hill, 1970 (Box-folder 10/18)
    - General Maintenance, 1970 (Box-folder 10/19)
    - Interim Operating Procedures: Relocation Assistance And Payments, 1970 (Box-folder 10/20)
    - Mapping, 1970 (Box-folder 10/21)
    - Pre-Construction – General, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 10/22)
    - Planning Surveys / Fatal Accidents, 1970 (Box-folder 10/23)
    - Right-of-Way – General, 1970 (Box-folder 10/24)
    - Safety, 1959-1970 (Box-folder 10/25)
    - Work Study Program, 1970 (Box-folder 10/26)
    - Advertising, 1972 (Box-folder 10/27)
    - Average Bidding Pricing, 1972 (Box-folder 10/28)
    - Campground and Beautification, 1972 (Box-folder 10/29)
    - Invitation for Bids, 1971 (Box-folder 10/30)
    - Bridge Maintenance and Inspection, 1972 (Box-folder 10/31)
    - Budget, 1972 (Box-folder 10/32)
    - Budget, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 10/33)
    - Building Program – 2 and 10 year plan, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 10/34)
    - Catastrophes / Natural Disaster, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 10/35)
    - City Ordinances, 1939-1969 (Box-folder 10/36)
    - Civil Defense, 1971 (Box-folder 10/37)
    - Construction – General, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 10/38)
    - Construction – General, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 10/39)
    - Culvert Pipe / Interstate 15, 1972 (Box-folder 10/40)
    - Department of the Army: Minutemen Access Records, 1973 (Box-folder 10/41)
    - Engineering / Construction Costs, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 10/42)
    - Monthly Construction Reports, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 10/43)
    - Monthly Construction Reports, 1972 (Box-folder 10/44)
    - Monthly Construction Reports, 1973 (Box-folder 10/45)
    - Monthly Construction Reports, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 10/46)
    - Army Missile Base, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 11/1)
    - Contract on Bootlegger Trail, 1971 (Box-folder 11/2)
    - Equipment Flasher Lights, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 11/3)
    - General Maintenance Estimates, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 11/4)
    - Gasoline / Fuel, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 11/5)
    - Highway Joint Development Council Meetings, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 11/6)
    - Highway Patrol / Fatal Accidents, 1972 (Box-folder 11/7)
    - Safety Projects – 5 Year Program, 1971 (Box-folder 11/8)
    - State Highway Commission Inspection Reports, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 11/9)
    - Wage Schedules, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 11/10)
    - Abandoned Right of Way, 1975-1979 (Box-folder 11/11)
    - Agreements, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/12)
    - Annexation – Right of Way, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 11/13)
    - Beautification Projects, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/14)
    - Bridges – Construction and Maintenance, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/15)
    - Budget, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/16)
    - Building Program – Long Range, 1978 (Box-folder 11/17)
    - Campground and Recreational Signing, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/18)
    - Contracts, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/19)
    - Disasters – Maintenance, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/20)
    - Emergency Energy Conservation, 1976-1980 (Box-folder 11/21)
    - Explosives, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/22)
    - Forest Service, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/23)
    - General Construction, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 11/24)
    - General Construction, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 11/25)
    - General Construction, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 11/26)
    - General Maintenance Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 11/27)
    - Hot Asphalt Plant Data, 1970-1979 (Box-folder 11/28)
    - Historical Sites Maintenance, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/29)
    - Laboratory – General, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/30)
    - Legislation and Organization, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/31)
    - Monthly Construction Report, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/32)
    - Missiles – Maintenance, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/33)
    - News Releases, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/34)
    - Open Pit Mining, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/35)
    - Personnel Policies, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 11/36)
    - Priority Budgeting and Planning, 1977 (Box-folder 11/37)
    - Public Hearings / Public Relations, 1976 (Box-folder 11/38)
    - Rest Area Maintenance, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/39)
    - Right of Way Subject Files, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 11/40)
    - Right of Way Encroachment and Excess Lands, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 11/41)
    - Road Surfaces Maintenance, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/42)
    - Secondary Roads Construction, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 11/43)
    - Seeing Projects, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 11/44)
    - State Highway Commission Inspection Reports, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 11/45)
    - State Highway Commission Inspection Reports, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 11/46)
    - Special Maintenance and Betterment, 1970 (Box-folder 12/1)
    - Signs and Signage, 1970 (Box-folder 12/2)
    - SPOT Improvement Safety Program, 1970 (Box-folder 12/3)
    - State Savings Fund Program, 1970 (Box-folder 12/4)
    - Snow Removal and Sanding, 1970 (Box-folder 12/5)
    - Signs and Signage, 1975 (Box-folder 12/6)
    - Signs and Signage, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 12/7)
    - Signs and Signals Construction, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 12/8)
    - Flood Damage and Repair, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 12/9)
    - Flood Damage and Repair, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 12/10)
    - Flood Repairs Costs, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 13/1)
    - Flood Control Documentation, 1986 (Box-folder 13/2)
    - Flood Repair Pondera County, 1986 (Box-folder 13/3)
    - Flood and Flood Costs, 1986 (Box-folder 13/4)
    - Flood Damage Accounts, 1986 (Box-folder 13/5)
    - Flood Damage Repair – Marias River and Dry Fork, 1986 (Box-folder 13/6)
    - Flood Damage Repair – Marias River and Dry Fork Construction Diary, 1986 (Box-folder 13/7)
    - Organizational Charts, 1984 (Box-folder 13/8)
- Havre Area Office, 1983-1998
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence: Index / Filing register, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 14/1)
    - Correspondence: Index / Filing register, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 14/2)
    - Correspondence: Index / Filing register, 1989 (Box-folder 14/3)
    - Correspondence: Index / Filing register, 1990 (Box-folder 14/4)
    - Correspondence, 1983 July-1988 June (Box-folder 14/5-62)
    - Correspondence, 1988 July-1993 (Box-folder 15)
    - Correspondence: Job Descriptions / Information, 1981 (Box-folder 16/1)
  - Meeting Minutes
    - AASHTO Highway Subcommittee on Maintenance, 1998 (Box-folder 16/2)
    - Area Maintenance Chiefs Meetings, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 16/3)
    - District Administrators Meetings, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 16/4)
    - District Staff Meetings (Great Falls), 1997-1999 (Box-folder 16/5)
    - District Staff Meetings (Great Falls), 2001 (Box-folder 16/6)
    - Field Maintenance Supervisors Meetings, 1997 (Box-folder 16/7)
    - Maintenance Management System Steering Committee Meeting, 1994 (Box-folder 16/8)
    - Maintenance Equipment Training Committee Meeting, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 16/9)
    - Maintenance Chief Meetings, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 16/10)
    - Safety Seminars, 1995-1999 (Box-folder 16/11)
    - Safety Committee / Accident Review, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 16/12)
    - Safety Committee / Accident Review, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 16/13)
    - Safety Committee / Accident Review, 1997-2000 (Box-folder 16/14)
    - Safety Committee / Accident Review, 1997 (Box-folder 16/15)
    - Safety Committee / Accident Review, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 16/16)
    - Safety Committee / Accident Review, 1995-1999 (Box-folder 16/17)
    - Section Safety Meetings, 1997 (Box-folder 16/18)
    - Section Supervisors Meetings, 1997, 1999 (Box-folder 16/19)
    - Section Supervisors Meeting s, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 16/20)
    - Sectionmen Meetings, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 16/21)
    - Shop Superintendant Meetings, 1995-1999 (Box-folder 16/22)
    - Sign Committee Meetings, 1994 (Box-folder 16/23)
    - Staff Meetings, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 16/24)
    - Staff Meetings, 1997 (Box-folder 16/25)
  - Subject Files
    - Work Plans: Cut Bank, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 16/26)
    - Supervisors' Area Spreadsheets, 1984-1995 (Box-folder 16/27)